We sigh whenever we're about to come to a standstill
終わりなき旅の途中　立ち止まりそうな時
Owarinaki tabi no tochuu tachidomarisouna toki
While moving on this endless journey.
深いため息こぼす　僕らは
Fukai tameiki kobosu bokura wa
Everytime we lunge for it, it escapes and flies off.
掴みかけてはまた離れていった
Tsukamikaketewa mata hanareteitta
But now, there's nothing to be afraid of
でも今はもう何も恐れることはない
Demo ima wa mou nanimo osoreru koto wa nai
The powerful ties that bind our hearts
心を繋ぐ強い絆は
Kokoro wo tsunagu tsuyoi kizuna wa
Will never come loose.
けして解けはしないさ
Keshite hodoke wa shinai sa
After a lifetime of searching, we finally arrived
探し続けて辿り着いた
Sagashitsuzukete tadoritsuita
Here, where the period lies.
この場所で Period に
Kono basho de piriodo ni
Let's change all our sorrow and rage to power.
悲しみ怒り 力に変えて
Kanashimi ikari chikara ni kaete
Destiny is right within our reach.
運命はすぐそばに
Unmei wa sugu soba ni
It's that expression again, May.
またこの表現だよ メイちゃん
Yeah, that also represents gold.
確かにそれも金を意味する言葉ですね
What are you two doing?
何してるの
We're checking to see whether there's a hidden message here.
隠された暗号がないか
調べているんだよ
A hidden message?
暗号
Alchemists often hide their research using trope and hidden meanings to prevent ordinary people from deciphering it.
錬金術は一般人が
簡単に解読できないよう
比喩や寓意を用いて
内容を秘匿するものなんだ
But at a glance, these documents aren't encrypted.
しかし  この研究書の場合
一見それがない
So we're going to note that phrases with "immortality" and "gold" appear quite often to try to view things differently.
そこで金とか
不老不死を意味する語句が
たくさん出てくることに着目して
調べ方を変えてみようかと
Think you're on to something then?
それで何か分かりそう
Not at all.
さっぱりです
Where am I?
ここは
Al!
アル
Sir Al!
アル様
I'm so glad!
よかった
I was worried you'd never wake up!
あのまま意識が戻らなかったら
どうしようかと…
Sorry for worrying all of you.
ごめん  心配掛けちゃったね
So, why am I in pieces?
ところで僕  なんでバラバラなの
And that's where we're at now.
というわけなの
You were too large to carry.
担いで移動しようにも
貴様は大きすぎるからな
That is why we had to take you apart.
それで分解させてもらった
Sorry to give you guys so much trouble.
ごめんなさい
みんなに迷惑を掛けてしまって
Has this ever happened before?
今までもこんなことあったの
Just once, while I was on my way here.
ここへ来る前にも一度
It must be inconvenient for you to be scattered in pieces.
いや  バラバラのままだと
君も何かと不便だろう
一度元の状態に戻そう
Let's put you back together.
Thanks, I appreciate it.
はい  お願いします
Could you hold on to this for a second?
ちょっと持っていてくれるかな
Let's see...
どれ
This is...
これは…
I think that's his right arm.
そっちは右腕ですね
Ah, you're right. We have to put him back together properly.
そうだね
組み合わせを間違えちゃいかんな
Scattered in pieces...
バラバラ…組み合わせ…
Putting things together...
Hey, May?!
ちょっと  メイちゃん
Look at what you've done!
なんてことを
They're all scattered now!
こんなにバラバラにしてしまって…
I was wondering...
組み合わせを変えて…
...how it would look if we changed the pages' order by grouping terms such as "gold" and "immortality".
金とか  不老不死とか
同じ語句の部分を重ねてみたら
どうなるかと思って
"Golden Being"... I saw that term over there.
「金の人」…
この単語はそっちにあったよ
"Immortality"... overlaps with these right here.
「不死」は…
こっちと重なりますよ
"Perfect Being"...
「完全なる人」は…
Ah, I found it!
あった  あった
Hand me those pages, Marcoh.
そのページをよこせ  マルコー
Oh, that ties into these!
それ  こっちとつながります
Does anyone have a "Golden Being"?
「黄金の人」はないか
あります  これです
I do. It's right here.
That should be the last of them.
これで最後
Could it be...
ひょっとして…
This is...
これは…
The Nationwide Transmutation Circle...
国土錬成陣…
Even if we find out about this now...
今更  これを知ったところで…
What does this mean?
どういうことだ
Do you mean these research documents won't be of any use at all?!
この研究書は
まったく役に立たねぇってことか
You've gotta be kidding me!
冗談じゃないぞ
What's going to happen to us-
オレたちは…いや
No...
What's going to happen to this country?!
この国はどうなる
I apologize...
すまない…
I was foolish to hope someone else's studies would overturn this crisis.
この危機的状況を逆転する手立てを
人の研究に求めた私が甘かった
Brother, is this what you wanted to tell me?
兄者
オレに伝えたかったのは
このことだったのか
Knowing you, shouldn't you have gotten further than this?
兄者ならもっと先まで
たどりついていたのではないのか
There's still something else.
まだ何かある
We didn't even realize to take it apart at first.
バラバラにも気づけなかったんだ
It wouldn't be strange if there was more hidden in these documents!
まだ何か…
隠された何かがあっても
おかしくないよ
Yeah.
Idiot! What were you thinking?!
てめぇ  何考えてんだ
It's Mother Nature's fault for making it so cold.
こんなに寒いのが悪いんだ
それでなくとも  私は冷え性で…
Besides, I'm sensitive to the cold!
So what?!
知るか
Now we don't know front from back!
どっちが表か裏か
分からなくなっちまったよ
Look at all these you flipped over!
ったく
派手にひっくり返しやがって
That may be it!
それかも
We need to "overturn" this crisis!
危機的状況を逆転させるんだよ
Flip each one of them over from how they were originally!
表と裏
今あったのをそのままひっくり返して
Well?
どう
Bingo.
当たりです
This is a new Amestrian Nationwide Transmutation Circle that is activated when Eastern Alchemy is made a part of it.
これは錬丹術を組み込んで発動する
新たなアメストリス国土錬成陣です
I don't see any signs of them going this way.
人が通った形跡はないようですし
道を間違えましたかね
Perhaps I took a wrong turn somewhere. I guess I'll go back.
戻りますか
I see.
なるほど
So this place is used to remove the rubble from the tunnel Sloth is digging.
スロウスが掘ってた
トンネルのがれきを出すために
ここが使われていたのですね
You're the Crimson Alchemist, correct?
紅蓮の錬金術師ですね
Pleasure to meet you. I'm Pride.
はじめまして  私はプライド
Can I help you?
何か私に用が
What happened with Scar?
スカーの件はどうなりました
I'm currently after him.
今  追跡中です
Save that for later.
あとにしなさい
First, carve a bloody crest into Briggs.
先にブリッグズに血の紋を刻むのです
With all due respect, the soldiers at Briggs are quite monolithic and powerful.
お言葉ですがブリッグズ兵の
一枚岩っぷりと強さは相当なもの
It won't be that easy.
簡単にいきそうもありませんよ
You need to utilize that exact strength.
その強さを利用するのです
The tunnel being dug by Sloth is almost complete.
スロウスが掘っているトンネルが
もうじき完成します
I understand.
分かりました
As you say, I'll carve a bloody crest.
血の紋を刻んでご覧に入れましょう
To the Briggs fortress.
ブリッグズの砦に
We've been waiting for you!
お待ちしておりました
何か変わったことは
Any changes?
Nothing in particular.
特には  それより
Moving right on, I heard Kimblee has gone missing. Is this true?
キンブリーが行方不明と聞きましたが
本当ですか
Yes.
そうだ
There was an explosion large enough to cause a shaft to collapse.
坑道が崩れるほどの爆発があってな
Kimblee and a few others are missing.
キンブリーほか数名が行方不明だ
We searched the rubble, but in the end, found no bodies.
さんざん捜索したが
結局誰の死体も出てこなかった
Are the "few others" soldiers from Briggs?
ほか数名とはブリッグズ兵ですか
No.
いや  キンブリーの部下２名と…
Two of Kimblee's men...
...and the Fullmetal Alchemist.
鋼の錬金術師だ
Oh. The Fullmetal boss, eh?
そうか  鋼の大将が…
I hope he's okay.
無事ならいいが
As do I.
How are things in the west?
西はどうですか
Things are getting nasty on the Pendleton border.
どうもこうも
ペンドルトンの国境戦は
ひでぇもんだったよ
From their way of fighting, I can't help but think they're trying  to produce more deaths.
わざと戦死者を出してるとしか
思えない戦い方をしてた
As you said, it seems like the army is taking the initiative in causing bloodshed to create a transmutation circle.
お前の言ったとおり
軍が錬成陣を作るために
率先して流血沙汰を起こしてるようだ
Have you gotten word from
Master Sergeant Fuery in the south?
南のフュリー曹長からは
連絡ありましたか
He called me a little while ago.
少し前に電話でな
He says they're having an all-out war with the Aerugon army in South Fotsett.
フォトセット南部で  アエルゴ軍と
ドンパチやってるそうだ
R... Run, Thomas!
は…走れ  トーマス
No time to rest!
休むな  トーマ…
Thoma-
Dammit!
ちくしょ
I will survive!
生き残ってやる
God dammit, I will  survive!!
絶対生き残ってやる
I see.
そうですか
After all, we, members of Mustang's old team, aren't so popular.
オレたち  元マスタング組は
それでなくても憎まれっ子だからな
Have you been in contact with the Colonel?
大佐には連絡つけてるのか
Yes, in full detail. We've been using a messenger who's acquainted with the Armstrong family.
アームストロング家ゆかりの
メッセンジャーを使って  逐一
Roger that.
そうか  北も大変そうだが気をつけろよ
Things seem to be getting pretty serious up north, so be careful.
Serious sounds about right.
大変…ですよね
The underlings of the man who's planning to turn this country into Hell are proceeding steadily with their plan,
この国を地獄に変えようってヤツの手下が
着々とその準備を進めてるってのに
but there's not a single thing we can do about it.
何一つ手出しできないんですから
It's connected.
つながった
I don't have to work anymore... right... Pride?
もう仕事  しないでいいか
プライド
The time is near.
もうすぐだ
The day is right within our reach.
その日はすぐそこだ
気をつけろ
Guys!
皆さん  ご飯ですよ
Lunch is served! Please line up!
並んでください
Hey Rose, I'd like to have meat pie next time.
ロゼ  オレ今度ミートパイが食いてぇな
We'll make some if we get the ingredients.
材料が入ったら作りますね
I'll be looking forward to it!
楽しみにしてるぜ
私  働いてないけど
I don't work here, but do you think you could possibly give these two something to eat?
この子らの分だけでも
分けてもらえないかねぇ
Why not?
もちろんです
There's plenty for you, too, madam.
おばあさんもどうぞ
おいしそうだ
This looks so good!
ロゼちゃん  大盛りでお願い
Can I get an extra scoop, Rose?
ダメですよ  みんな平等です
Sorry, everyone gets the same amount.
Excuse me...
あの…すみません…
わ…私にも下さい…
C-Can I have some, as well?
You saved me!
いや  助かった
Thank you so much. It was great.
ありがとう  ごちそうさま
Where did you come from?
お前さんどこから来たんだい
どこからでもないね
That's a difficult question to answer,
since I've been wandering all over the place.
あちこち  ウロウロしているんで
But why Lior of all places?
何しにこんな所まで
You've heard of the riot that happened here, right?
ご存じでしょ
ここであった暴動のこと
There's nothing left in this town because of it.
そのせいでここは  何もない町に
なってしまったんです
There are delicious meals here, are there not?
こんなにおいしい食事があるのに
I'm flattered by your compliment,
そう言っていただけると
うれしいですけど…
but this is about all I can do to help.
自分にはこれくらいのことしかできないから
そんなことないよ
That's not true.
Both the warm meals you serve and the bright smile on your face motivate everyone to work.
温かい食事とお嬢さんの笑顔が
みんなの力になってる
That's right.
そうだ
I know you just saved my life,
but I'm actually looking for a church.
世話になったついでと言っちゃあなんだが
教会を探しているんだが
教会
A church?
Yeah. The headquarters of the Leto religion, the cause of the riot.
そう  暴動の原因になったっていう
レト教の本部
It's just as you see.
ご覧の有様だ
Even if you go in, there won't be anything left.
今更入っても何もないよ
Is there a passage that leads underground?
地下に下りる通路はあるかな
Y-Yes, there is, but...
あるにはありますけど…
これは
What's this?
A poisoned reservoir.
毒の水です
It was already like that when we found it.
いつの間にかこうなっていたんです
So an ordinary human won't be able to get past this.
普通の人間はこの先に
進めないようになっているのか
Let's see.
どれ
待って
Wait!
You'll die if you step in it!
入ったら死んじまう
奇跡の業…
A miracle...
You mean... alchemy...
じゃなくて
錬金術…ですよね…
ちょっと奥まで行ってきますんで
I'm going to go a bit further,
so could you wait for me here?
待っててくれます
Wow...
This place is huge.
でかいな
Damn him, making something so large.
ったく
大層なもの作りやがってん
That was quick.
いきなり当たりか
あら  足止めにもならないな
Uh oh, that wasn't even enough to slow you down.
なら…
In that case...
Why don't I trap you?!
閉じ込めてみるか
Uh oh...
あらら…
This isn't good...
参ったね  こりゃ…
What's wrong? Aren't you going to kill me?
どうした  かかってこないのか
Hmm?
You... You're Van Hohenheim, aren't you?
その姿  ヴァン·ホーエンハイムか
Looks like this is as far as you can go.
どうやらここまでがお前の入れ物らしいな
You'll die if you go any further?
ここを出ると死ぬ…か
Going past this line will result in your death, right?
一定ラインを越えると
死んでしまうのだろう
Kind of like that flask.
あのときのフラスコのように
So, my conclusion is you can only move within this tunnel and in the center portion of Central.
このトンネル内と
セントラルの中心部でしか
動けないとみたが  どうだ
What do you say?
Am I right?
図星か
What's wrong? Why don't you say something, Mr. Can't-Leave-His-Home?!
どうした
なんとか言ったらどうだ
引きこもりめ
You mad?
怒ってる
There's no such thing as wrath within me.
怒りなど
私の中には存在しません
Not just wrath.
怒りだけではありません
I left all of my unnecessary emotions within Father.
いらぬ感情は
父上の中に置いてきました
My name is Pride.
私の名はプライドです
Pride...
プライド…なるほど 「傲慢」か
I see, so that stands for "avarice".
They say man is embodied by seven deadly sins.
人には七つの罪があるという
色欲
Lust.
Greed.
強欲
Sloth.
怠惰
暴食
Gluttony.
嫉妬
Envy.
Wrath.
憤怒
And... Pride.
そして  傲慢
あいつが最初に切り離したのがお前
So the emotion he let go of first was you. "Pride".
プライドだったってわけだ
ご丁寧にフラスコの中に
Funny how he detached you to look exactly as he did when he was in the flask.
いたころの姿と似せて切り離すとは
So that appearance itself is the true nature of that arrogant, self-adulating father of yours.
その姿こそが
傲慢で自尊心の強いあいつ
お前の父親の本質か
I'm going to ask that you visit my father.
父上のところに来ていただこうか
Hey, no need to rush things.
そう焦るなよ
呼ばれなくても行ってやるさ
Don't worry; I'd visit him even if I weren't invited.
Tell him this:
あいつに伝えろ
そのうち奴隷２３号が会いに行く
"Slave Number 23 will be coming to see you soon."
"Throw yourself back in your chair in Central while you wait for him."
せいぜい  セントラルで
ふんぞり返って待っていろ…とな
Got it?
Sure, I'll be waiting for you.
待っているぞ
Van Hohenheim.
ヴァン·ホーエンハイム
He's back.
帰って来た
Find anything?
何かあったかい
Yeah...
一般人は近寄らない方がいいね
People shouldn't go near this place. It's dangerous.
危ないから
Please tell everyone not to go in.
誰も入らないように
言っておいてください
What were you doing down there?
奥で何してきたんですか
Just a little declaration of war.
宣戦布告
交代だ
Your shift is up.
Finally! The blizzard was killing me!
待ってました
吹雪で大変だった
さて  まずいコーヒーでも飲んでくっか
I guess I'll go have a cup of bad coffee.
Good work.
お疲れさん
H-Hey!
まさか  あれは…
Don't tell me that's...
The Drakman army?!
ドラクマだ
Drakma to the north has declared open hostilities!
北のドラクマより  開戦宣言あり
総員  戦闘配備  繰り返す
All men, battle positions!
I repeat!
北のドラクマより  開戦宣言あり
Drakma to the north has declared open hostilities!
総員  戦闘配備
All men, battle positions!
We're lucky the Northern Wall of Briggs isn't around.
「ブリッグズの北壁」が
不在とは有り難いことだ
Right, Sir Kimblee?
のう  キンブリー殿
Additionally, there are many men loyal to me in the fort.
それに加え
こちらの手の者が砦の中に多数います
Once the battle begins, they'll betray the others, causing the fort to be thrown into confusion.
戦闘が始まれば  内応し
砦を混乱に陥れるでしょう
At last, I shall take Briggs by storm.
我がドラクマが
長く越えることのできなかったブリッグズを
今日こそ攻略してみせようぞ
The fort that has stood in the way of Drakma for eternity!
It's time for the declaration of war.
さあ  宣戦布告ですよ
Let's launch some fireworks, shall we?!
派手に花火を
打ち上げようじゃないですか
All cannons at the ready!
全砲  撃ち方  用意
撃てっ
Fire!!!
The promise we never made
交わしたはずのない約束が
Kawashita hazu no nai yakasoku ga
yet again
今日も
Kyou mo
tries to snatch our future away from us.
僕らの未来を奪おうとする
Bokura no mirai wo ubaou to suru
Why is it that we can't rejoice
欲しがっていたものを手にしても
Hoshigatteita mono wo te ni shitemo
straight from the heart
素直に
Sunao ni
when we obtain something we've always been after?
うまく笑えないのはなぜだろう
Umaku waraenai nowa nazedarou
The overflowing tears aren't from feebleness or remorse.
あふれる涙は　弱さや後悔じゃない
Afureru namida wo yowasa ya koukai ja nai
They're fragments born from agony.
イタミが生んだカケラで
Itami ga unda kakera de
Of all the moments and destinies,
どんな瞬間だって運命だって
Donna shunkan datte unmei datte
I realized there's one absolute certainty.
ひとつだけ確かなものがあると知った
Hitotsu dake tashika na mono ga aru to shitta
Even if things get tough and I'm at my limit
限界だって困難だって
Genkai datte konnan datte
I refuse to give up.
あきらめたくないよ
Akirametakunaiyo
Please, don't let go.
このまま離さないで
Konomama hanasanaide
I can feel the warmth of your right hand
かたく握りしめた　君の右手のぬくもり
Kataku nigirishimeta kimi no migite no nukumori
where it's tightly joined with my left.
ここにあるから
Koko ni arukara
Yeah, that's right. My name is Zampano.
そうだ
オレの名はザンパノ
キンブリーの部下だ
One of Kimblee's men.
Doctor Marcoh is currently hiding in the slums of Asbec.
ドクター·マルコーが
アスベック村のスラムに潜伏中だ
I appreciate you telling us, Zampano.
よく教えてくれた  ザンパノ
We'll guarantee your safety.
お前の身は保障してやる
マルコー
Marcoh!
楽しくなってきたよ
Things are getting interesting!
Wily souls bring about a catastrophe,
日本語字幕仕上げ：XIAOBIN
悪らつな魂は惨禍をもたらし
決断する矜持はその身に傷を負う
and the pride making the decision gets hurt in the process.
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
だが  避けられない
But it's inevitable in the process of rebirth.
生まれ変わるためには
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
次回　鋼の錬金術師
Fullmetal  Alchemist
第４３話　『蟻のひと噛み』
Episode 43, Bite of the Ant.
雪原が赤く染まる
The snowfield is dyed red.
守るために流された  血の色に
The color of blood that was shed to protect.